<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="marquard@ched.uct.ac.za">Stephen Marquard</author>
        <title>Collaborative writing exercise in an undergraduate course</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Actors">
            <ul>
                <li> Phumzile is the course convenor for a 3rd-year undergraduate course in Economics of Developing Countries.</li>
                <li> Reza is one of 10 tutors teaching on the course, responsible for a tutor group of 12 students.</li>
                <li> Susan, Bongani and Jonathan are students in Reza’s tutor group.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="Use Case">
            <subsection name="Task" >
                <p>
                    Phumzile requires students, working in groups of 3, to choose one of 4
                    developing countries (Brazil, India, Nigeria and South Africa) and
                    write together an assessment of that country’s economic development
                    over the last 3 decades.  
                </p>
                <p>
                    Phumzile
                    decides that a wiki would be an appropriate tool to facilitate students
                    collaboratively writing their assessments. Previously this type of
                    exercise had been done with Word documents using track changes, but
                    that required lots of emailing revised documents around, and made it
                    hard for students to work on their group assignments at the same
                    time.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Setup" >
                <p>
                    As the course already has a course site created for it in the Sakai
                    environment, Phumzile creates a template wiki with some instructions
                    about the assignment on the home page, and then creates 12 wikis (one
                    for each tutor group) from the template wiki.</p>
                <p>Phumzile
                    would like to discourage students borrowing work from other groups, so
                    the wikis are configured by default so that no students have access to
                    any wiki. Phumzile assigns administration rights for each wiki to the
                    respective tutor for that tutor group.
                </p>
                <p>Reza
                    prepares for the first tutorial session with his tutor group by logging
                    into the Sakai environment, and granting students in his tutor group
                    read and update permissions to the tutor group’s wiki.
                </p>
                <p>Reza explains
                    the assignment to the students, who organize themselves into 4 project
                    groups of 4 students. Each project group chooses a different country.
                    All students in the tutor group will use the same wiki for their work,
                    although each project group will be working on a different country in
                    different pages of the wiki.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Collaboration" >
                <p>
                    Susan, Bongani and Jonathan login to the course site, where they see 
                    the wiki for their tutor group appear. Over a period of several weeks, 
                    they each write a section of the assignment, then collate them together, 
                    and do some editing of each others’ work to create a coherent composite
                    document.
                </p>
                <p>
                    They find it useful to look at how the other project groups in their 
                    tutorial groups are tackling their assignments on other countries,
                    but do not have access to the work of students in other tutorial
                    groups, so cannot compare their own work with any other students 
                    working on the same country.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Assesment" >
                <p>
                    On the due date for the assignment to be handed in, Susan creates a 
                    PDF of their set of pages from the wiki, and submits the PDF for 
                    assessment using the Assignment handin tool.
                </p>
                <p>                    
                    Reza assesses the assignment, and allocates it a mark. However, 
                    because a component of the final mark for each student is based on
                    his or her respective contribution to the project group’s effort,
                    Reza also logs into the course environment, and views the wiki 
                    contribution history of each student in turn.
                </p>
                <p>                    
                    The contribution history shows the changes and additions that the 
                    student made to the wiki. Reza notices that Susan and Bongani made 
                    extensive input and contributions, whereas Jonathan's changes were 
                    less frequent and of a less substantive nature, so awards a higher 
                    contribution mark to Susan and Bongani than to Jonathan.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Comments" >
            <ol>
                <li> Limiting access to a group of users witin a Worksite will
                    require an ACL structure to the Wiki pages within the Worksite. When
                    Hierachy and Super Structure services appear in 2.1.<ol>
                        <li> In 2.0 this could be achieve by seperate worksited for each group, linked when required into the course site.</li>
                    </ol></li>
                <li> There are no new requirements from Collaboration that cant be handled by the 2.0 release</li>
                <li> Assessment<ol>
                    <li> Need for a PDF export of a group of pages.</li>
                </ol></li>
                
            </ol><br/>
            Please say if my interpretation of the use case is correct ?
        </section>
    </body>
    <!--    
        <body>
        <section name="Actors">
        </section>
        <section name="Use Case">
        </section>
        </body>
    -->
</document>
