<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="gdoyle@its.uct.ac.za"> Greg Doyle</author>
        <title>Role playing in an undergraduate course</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Actors">
            <ul>
                <li>  Frank is the course convenor for a 3rd-year undergraduate course</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="Use Case">
            <subsection name="Setup" >
                <p>
                    Students are allocated different country names, one of eight 
                    different issues they need to look at as well as belonging to 
                    one of two sub-committees.
                    They each have to a central online course environment as well 
                    as 1 of 8 different environments depending which issue they need 
                    to look at.
                    In each of the 2 environments they belong to their country name 
                    and which sub-committee they are members of need to be displayed
                     and not their real names/ids.
                 </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Task" >
                <p>
                    Frank requires the students to make available, in the central 
                    course, information regarding their country. This counts towards
                     their final mark.
                </p>
                <p>
                    They also need to interact with other countries on a global 
                    scale, those looking at the same issue they are as well as with 
                    countries in the same sub-committee.
                    They therefore heavily utilised the communication tools 
                    (forum and chat) made available in the 2 course environments to 
                    interact with one another.
                </p>
                <p>                    
                    The course environment also keeps track of the number of 
                    postings made by each student which is used in allocating 
                    a mark. The students also have access to the log files of 
                    the chat sessions which acts as the minutes of their meetings.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Comments" >
            <p>                
            Although this use case adds requirements to collaboration in general 
            ( discussion, chat ), and I believe that any tools of that type should
             address the issues raised, however I am not certain that a Wiki is the
              best tool for this purpose since it provides a very unstructured 
              environment. If anyone feels that I have got this wrong, and the use 
              case outlines requirements for a wiki, please say.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
    <!--    
        <body>
        <section name="Actors">
        </section>
        <section name="Use Case">
        </section>
        </body>
    -->
</document>
