<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="ian@caret.cam.ac.uk">Ian Boston</author>
        <title>RWiki Software Requirements Specification</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Actors">
            <ul>
                <li> Harry is the leader of a research group</li>
                <li> Judy is a researcher</li>
                <li> Roberta is a reasearch group leader in a Italian University</li>
                <li> James is a copyright and IPR lawyer used by the organisation</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="Use Case">
            <p> Harry has identified an opportunity for his research group with one of the EU
                funding bodies. To build a better case for funding his research he decides to
                collaborate with an Intalian University and agrees with a colleague in that
                University, Roberta. Harry sets up a worksite in the Sakai and adds a Discussion
                Tool, a Resources Tool and an Wiki Tool. Since they need to explore the outline
                agreement of their collaboration, Harry creates a workspace within the Wiki and
                gives members of the worksite access to the collaboration space. He then sends an
                email to Roberta inviting her to join the worksite. </p>
            <p> She joins the worksite and begins to outline what her research group has to offer in
                the area, and what her research group has done in the past that is relevant to this
                proposal. Together they begin to build a Wiki space that contains the basis for
                their propsal. After several days they have an issue over shared copyright. They
                bring together some of the documents and publish them as PDF's using the Wiki PDF
                tool. They put these into the Sakai resources area and send them to James to answer
                the questions about shared copyright and IPR. It becomes clear that James needs more
                information and the email exchanges are getting in the way of collaboration. James
                joins the worksite in Sakai and is given access to the Wiki workspace by virtue of
                his membership of the worksite. He reviews the source documentation and makes some
                changes to specific wording. Harry and Roberto are monitoring the pages for changes
                by email notification so are aware of all the changes that have been made. </p>
            <p> As the detail of the workschedule is being developed the core team need to ask for
                the opinion of Judy. Harry changes the permissions on some sensitive documents and
                invites Judy to join the Sakai worksite. Judy reviews the areas that concern certain
                aspects of the research. Judy references some content from previous research work
                sites and copies some of the supporting material into the resources area. </p>
            <p> Finally the team build a proposal document that is converted to PDF and delivered as
                the final proposal. </p>
            <p>Alternatives would include: <ul class="star">
                <li> the draft proposal is converted to Open Office document format or Microsoft
                    Word and final editing is done within version control in that application</li>
                <li> sections of the draft proposal are cut and pasted into a Word application
                    form supplied by the funding agency</li>
            </ul>
            </p>
            <p> 3 months later the grant is awarded, Harry and Roberto create a new Wiki space
                within the Sakai Workspace and begin planning the implementation. The original
                proposal workspace is restricted to the members of the management committee. </p>
        </section>
    </body>
    <!--    
        <body>
        <section name="Actors">
        </section>
        <section name="Use Case">
        </section>
        </body>
    -->
</document>
