<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0b5/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">

    <info>
        <title>Provisional Tools</title>
        <edition>14 July 2006 – Document version 2.2</edition>
    </info>

    <sect1 xml:id="provisional">
        <title>What Makes a Tool Provisional</title>
        <para>A provisional tool is one which is considered to be mature enough to be included in
            the release distribution, but is not (yet) considered to be an official part of the
            enterprise bundle, and which does not come enabled by default. Additional steps are
            required to enable these additional tools, per the discretion of the deploying
            institutions or individuals.</para>
        <para>However, a provisional tool may meet a need that the standard tools do not. Since one
            of the criteria for provisional status is that the tool must already have seen
            successful production use at more than one member institution, and since provisional
            tools are included in the code QA'ed before release, you should be able to deploy a
            provisional tool in production with some confidence, provided the proper configuration
            is done in advance.</para>
        <para>The basic idea of a provisional tools is to allow sites to have ready access to
            blossoming tools for testing and evaluation. If they meet needs and broad success is
            reported in production, they may be included as a standard part of the bundle in future
            releases. Your feedback on the suitability of these tools for inclusion in an upcoming
            Sakai release is therefore an important part of this process.</para>
        <para>You'll find a more complete description of the criteria for provisional status among
            the "community practices" posted on Confluence: <link
                xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/SCP/Criteria+for+Provisional+Status"
                >Criteria for Provisional Status</link></para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="unstealth">
        <title>Unstealthing Tools</title>
        <para>Provisional tools are, as a general rule, "stealthed" by default. This means they do
            not appear as options in either the <emphasis>Worksite Setup</emphasis> or
                <emphasis>Edit Tools</emphasis> lists - they effectively require the intervention of
            an admin in order to be added to a site.</para>
        <para>Tools can be stealthed through a setting in <filename>sakai.properties</filename>,
            which simply contains a comma-separated list of all the tool ids for stealthed tools.
            Sakai OOTB has the following tools stealthed:</para>
        <screen>
stealthTools@org.sakaiproject.tool.api.ActiveToolManager=sakai.assignment,sakai.rwiki,sakai.site.roster,
osp.evaluation,osp.exposedmatrix,osp.exposedwizard,osp.glossary,osp.guidance.sample,osp.matrix,osp.presTemplate,
osp.presentation,osp.reports,osp.synoptic,osp.synoptic.design.publish,osp.wizard,sakai.messagecenter,
sakai.metaobj,sakai.postem,sakai.rwiki,sakai.samigo,sakai.search,sakai.site.roster,sakai.sitemanage,
osp.presLayout,osp.style</screen>
        <para>There are some provisional tools (e.g. SU, Sakaiscript, Summary Calendar) for which
            stealthing does not apply, since they are inherently designed for admin enabling and
            deployment. These tools are not registered for <emphasis>Worksite Setup</emphasis> in
            the first place, and so are effectively always stealthed.
            Stealthing is a mechanism for obscuring tools from site creators and maintainers, not
            admins, who always have access to all the available tools.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="tool-list">
        <title>Provisional Tools in 2.2.0</title>
        <sect2 xml:id="samigo">
            <title>Tests&amp;Quizzes</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>sakai.samigo</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/SAM/Home"
                                >http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/SAM/Home</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Lydia Li (lydial@stanford.edu)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para>Samigo is the historical project name for the tool that appears in Sakai as
                        <emphasis>Tests&amp;Quizzes</emphasis> (the terms are often used
                    interchangeably). It is an online assessment tool that supports teaching and
                    learning, in both formative assessments and summative assessments.</para>

                <para>Its key features are:</para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Creating Assessments</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>It supports rich text editing of a variety of question types such
                                as Multiple Choice, Survey, Short Answer/Essay, True/False, Fill in
                                the Blank, File Upload...etc.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Importing/Exporting</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Assessments can be exported/imported via IMS QTI xml format</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Organizing and Publishing</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>with options for specifying release date, due date, and/or retract
                                date, late handling, number of submissions, grading options,
                                feedback settings, and layout...etc Auto and manual grading;
                                Managing question pool</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Managing assessment-taking</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>such as randomized tests, random draw from question pool, timed
                                assessment with auto submit, high security assessments with
                                restricted IP and secondary password, as well as option to send
                                grades to Sakai's Gradebook tool.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>Simply unstealth the tool to begin using it in sites. It requires no special
                    configuration.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="rwiki">
            <title>Rwiki</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>sakai.rwiki</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link
                                xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/RWIKI/Home"
                                >http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/RWIKI/Home</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Ian Boston (ian@caret.cam.ac.uk)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para>RWiki is an open-source Wiki tool for Sakai that gives worksite members the
                    ability to create and update wiki pages within the worksite. RWiki is designed
                    and developed at the Centre for Applied Research into Educational Technology
                    (CARET) at Cambridge Univeristy.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>No special configuration required.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="messagecenter">
            <title>Message Center</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>sakai.messagecenter</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/MFT/Home"
                                >http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/MFT/Home</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Kristol Hancock (khancock@iupui.edu)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para>Message Center is Indiana University’s solution for discussion and private
                    messaging, facilitating one-on-one and group communication. Through private
                    messaging, users within a site can quickly and easily communicate and can even
                    auto-forward private messages to their favorite email client. By providing
                    authors with extensive control over permissions and forum/topic status and
                    giving users a more intuitive navigation, the discussion forum feature
                    complements private messaging well.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>System administrators need to set the role-to-permission-level mapping in
                        <filename>sakai.properties</filename>. OOTB generic roles are set to the
                    following:</para>
                <screen>
mc.default.Student=Contributor
mc.default.Instructor=Owner</screen>
                <para>Note: If you add a role to <filename>sakai.properties</filename> that has a
                    space, you must escape it with a backslash (e.g., <command>mc.default.project\
                        owner=Owner</command>).</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="osp">
            <title>OSP (several related tools)</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>osp.*</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/OSP/Home"
                                >http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/OSP/Home</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Chris Coppola (chris.coppola@rsmart.com)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>The several OSP tools support the use of online portfolios, and are designed to
                work in concert. The number of tools and purposes is too great to take on here, so
                please visit <link xl:href="http://www.osportfolio.org"
                >http://www.osportfolio.org</link> for more information on the Open Source Portfolio
                (OSP).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="search">
            <title>Search</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>sakai.search</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link
                                xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/SEARCH/Home"
                                >http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/SEARCH/Home</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Ian Boston (ian@caret.cam.ac.uk)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para>The search tool aims to provide a tool that allows a Google like search all
                    content in a Sakai instance.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>You may change the following settings in sakai.properties:</para>
                <screen>
#indexStorageName@org.sakaiproject.search.index.IndexStorage = filesystem
#indexStorageName@org.sakaiproject.search.index.IndexStorage = cluster
indexStorageName@org.sakaiproject.search.index.IndexStorage = db
recoverCorruptedIndex@org.sakaiproject.search.index.IndexStorage = false
location@org.sakaiproject.search.index.IndexStorage = tableName|localDirectory</screen>

                <para>The <command>indexStorageName</command> is the name of the configured class
                    that is used for index storage.</para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>filesystem</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>stores the file on the localfilesystem and assumes the system is
                                being run either as a single node, or with a shared
                            filesystem.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>db</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>stores the index in the sakai database</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>cluster</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>stores the index on local filesystems but performs clusterwide
                                updates as the index is updated. This mechanism relies on a unix
                                shell script to perform the synchronisation, so will need local
                                configuration.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>

                <para><command>recoverCorruptedIndex</command> controls what happens if the index is
                    found to be corrupt. If true, the index can be automatically deleted and
                    restarted, but it will have no content. The content can be re-initialised by
                    admin rebuilding the index of the whole instance. If false a corrupted index
                    will cause an exception to be reported to the end user.</para>

                <para><command>location</command> is the location of the index. If the driver is a
                    database driver, the location will be a database table. If the driver is a
                    filesystem it will be a directory where the index files are stored.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="su">
            <title>SU</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>sakai.su</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>None</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Zach Thomas (zach.thomas@txstate.edu)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para>SU is a tool for administrators to use to log in as another user. It is code
                    developed at Texas State University for their local brand of Sakai called
                        <emphasis>TRACS: Teaching Research and Collaboration System</emphasis>. It
                    is meant to be used within the Admin Workspace, and so it does not need to be
                    stealthed or unstealthed (it will never appear among the tool options in
                    "Worksite Setup"). It features a simple form in which you type the user id of
                    the user you wish to "become" in the system.</para>
                <para>The name stands for Super User, and comes from a command-line tool in Unix
                    that serves the same purpose. It is often pronounced "Sue."</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>

                <para>In order to use the tool, edit the <emphasis>!admin</emphasis> site (i.e. the
                    Admin MyWorkspace) through the admin <emphasis>Sites</emphasis> tool, add a page
                    or edit an existing page, and place the tool on that page. The SU tool will
                    appear in the list with the title "Become User" and the id
                    <emphasis>sakai.su</emphasis>. When you've placed the tool, remember to click
                    the <emphasis>Save</emphasis> button.</para>

                <para>The tool itself is very simple. There is a text field to type a user id, and
                    there is a <emphasis>Submit</emphasis> button. Your session will continue as
                    though you had logged in as the specified user. This will work even if that user
                    is already logged in at another location.</para>

                <para>To change back to "yourself," you must logout and log back in.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Security</title>
                <para>The SU tool is hard-coded only to work for users with administrative
                    privileges. Naturally you should take care whom you give these privileges to.
                    The ability to have more fine-grained control of permissions on the tool may be
                    developed for a future version.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="sakaiscript">
            <title>Sakaiscript</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>NA</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>None</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Steve Githens (s-githens@northwestern.edu)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para>Sakaiscript is essentially a logical web service wrapper to the Sakai API,
                    opening up a number of common admin functions to easy scripting from other
                    languages.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>Sakai web services and SakaiScript are included in the release and need to be
                    turned on using a property in the Sakai Properties file:</para>
                <screen>
# Indicates whether or not we allow web-service logins
webservices.allowlogin=false</screen>
                <para>This parameter is set to false so as to make sure that no one can robot-guess
                    Sakai passwords using web services out of the box. If you want to support the
                    login and session-establishment, you must set this proprty to true in your Sakai
                    instance.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Security</title>
                <para>Any site enabling web-services should understand the security implications of
                    Sakai web services. Web services should be run over HTTPS in any production
                    environment as IDs, Passwords, and Sakai Session Keys are passed back and forth
                    in plain text using SOAP.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>



        <sect2 xml:id="postem">
            <title>Post 'Em</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>sakai.postem</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/PEM/Home"
                                >http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/PEM/Home</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Kristol Hancock (khancock@iupui.edu)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para><emphasis>Post ‘Em</emphasis> is an automated reporting system that enables
                    faculty to post grades and comments without compromising student privacy.
                        <emphasis>Post ‘Em</emphasis> accepts CSV files, empowering faculty to track
                    student grades in a spreadsheet application of their choice. Keep in mind that
                        <emphasis>Post ‘Em</emphasis> files are not restricted to grades and
                    comments, so the research community may also benefit from this
                functionality.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>The tool simply needs to be unstealthed, and requires no special
                    configuration.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="summarycalendar">
            <title>Summary Calendar</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>sakai.summary.calendar</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link
                                xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/CALSUM/Calendar+Summary"
                                >http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/CALSUM/Calendar+Summary</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Nuno Fernandes (nuno@ufp.pt)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>
                <link
                    xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/CALSUM/Calendar+Summary"
                    >Confluence Space</link>
            </para>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para>Calendar Summary is a synoptic tool for Sakai 2.1.x and 2.2.x that presents a
                    visual monthly view of schedule events in the Home page of My Workspace or other
                    course/project site. If placed on My Workspace sites, it aggregates schedule
                    events of all active sites the user is member of (except if user is admin). If
                    placed on course/project sites, it presents only events of that site.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>This tool may be unstealthed to allow it to be added by site maintainers -
                    just as with most other provisional tools, but it may also be particularly
                    appropriate to add it to all new MyWorkspaces by default, and this can be done
                    by editing the appropriate site template: <command>!user</command> for My
                    Workspace sites; <command>!worksite</command> for course/project sites. </para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="roster">
            <title>Roster</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>sakai.site.roster</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>None</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Kristol Hancock (khancock@iupui.edu)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para><emphasis>Roster</emphasis> allows users to view the names, photos and
                    profiles of site participants who have made their information accessible through
                    the <emphasis>Profile</emphasis> tool in <emphasis>My Workspace</emphasis>. If
                    an institution has institutional photos, the photos can be made accessible
                    separately to site maintainers.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>The tool simply needs to be unstealthed, and requires no special
                    configuration.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="twinpeaks">
            <title>TwinPeaks</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>None</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>None</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Jim Eng (jimeng@umich.edu)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para>TwinPeaks is a capability to search external repositories while using the
                    HTMLArea WYSIWIG editor (note: Sakai 2.2 uses FCKeditor by default). TwinPeaks
                    was originally developed by the Indiana University Library and was extended and
                    merged into the Sakai 2.1 release by the MIT OKI project.</para>

                <para>To add a repository to TwinPeaks, one must write or obtain an OKI DR OSID
                    implementation for that particular repository and then install the OSID
                    implementation in their Sakai instance. Documentation for installing and
                    registering a new OSID implementation within Sakai is available in the Sakai
                    Development Resources area on collab.sakiaproject.org.</para>
                <para>TwinPeaks is suitable for use on development servers and can be used to enable
                    sites to begin the development of their DR OSID implementations. The TwinPeaks
                    implementation in the Sakai 2.2 release should not be turned on in production
                    systems without additional work.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>TwinPeaks can be enabled by changing the following sakai.properties setting to
                    true.</para>

                <screen>
# enable the twinpeaks feature in the WYSIWYG editor in legacy tools: true or false
wysiwyg.twinpeaks=false</screen>

            </sect3>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</article>
