<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0b5/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">

    <info>
        <title>Provisional Tools</title>
        <edition>14 July 2006 - Document version 2.2</edition>
    </info>

    <sect1 xml:id="provisional">
        <title>What Makes a Tool Provisional</title>
        <para>A provisional tool is one which is considered to be mature enough to be included in
            the release distribution, but is not (yet) considered to be an official part of the
            enterprise bundle, and which does not come enabled by default. Additional steps are
            required to enable these extra tools.</para>
        <para>However, a provisional tool may meet a need that the standard tools do not. Since one
            of the criteria for provisional status is that the tool must already have seen
            successful production use at more than one member institution, and since provisional
            tools are included in the code QA'ed for a release, you should be able to deploy a
            provisional tool in production with some confidence.</para>
        <para>The basic idea of provisional tools is to allow implementors to have ready access to
            blossoming tools for testing and evaluation. If they meet needs and broad success is
            reported in production, they may be included as a standard part of the bundle in future
            releases. Your feedback on the suitability of these tools for inclusion in an upcoming
            Sakai release is therefore an important part of this process.</para>
        <para>You'll find a more complete description of the criteria for provisional status among
            the "community practices" posted on Confluence: <link
                xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/SCP/Criteria+for+Provisional+Status"
                >Criteria for Provisional Status</link></para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="unstealth">
        <title>Unstealthing Tools</title>
        <para>Provisional tools are, as a general rule, "stealthed" by default. This means they do
            not appear as options in either the <emphasis>Worksite Setup</emphasis> or
                <emphasis>Edit Tools</emphasis> lists - they effectively require the intervention of
            an admin in order to be added to a site.</para>
        <para>Tools can be stealthed through a setting in <filename>sakai.properties</filename>,
            which simply contains a comma-separated list of all the tool ids for those tools that
            will be stealthed. Sakai OOTB has the following tools stealthed:</para>
        <screen>
stealthTools@org.sakaiproject.tool.api.ActiveToolManager=sakai.assignment,sakai.rwiki,sakai.site.roster,
osp.evaluation,osp.exposedmatrix,osp.exposedwizard,osp.glossary,osp.guidance.sample,osp.matrix,osp.presTemplate,
osp.presentation,osp.reports,osp.synoptic,osp.synoptic.design.publish,osp.wizard,sakai.messagecenter,
sakai.metaobj,sakai.postem,sakai.samigo,sakai.search,sakai.sitemanage,
osp.presLayout,osp.style</screen>
        <para>To unstealth a tool, simply remove it from this list in
            <filename>sakai.properties</filename>.</para>
        <para>There are some provisional tools (e.g. <emphasis>SU</emphasis>,
            <emphasis>Sakaiscript</emphasis>, <emphasis>Summary Calendar</emphasis>) for which
            stealthing is not an issue, since they are inherently designed for admin enabling and
            deployment. These tools are not registered for <emphasis>Worksite Setup</emphasis> in
            the first place, and so are effectively always stealthed. Stealthing is a mechanism for
            obscuring tools from site creators and maintainers, not admins, who have access to all
            the available tools through their admin site functions.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="tool-list">
        <title>Provisional Tools in 2.2.0</title>
        <para>A brief overview of each provisional tool is provided below. For more detailed
            information visit the Confluence links provided, or send your questions to the listed
            contact.</para>

        <sect2 xml:id="rwiki">
            <title>Rwiki</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>sakai.rwiki</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link
                                xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/RWIKI/Home"
                                >http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/RWIKI/Home</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Ian Boston (ian@caret.cam.ac.uk)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para>The Wiki tool is a fully integrated Sakai Tool that enables users of Sakai to
                    create content, share and manage in a Wiki Environment. Where functionality is
                    provided by other tools within Sakai, the wiki delegates responsibility to those
                    tools (e.g. resources).</para>



                <para>Additional functionality includes:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Linking between worksite spaces</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Adding content from the Resources tool (e.g. images)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Creating subspaces within worksite spaces</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Controlling permissions</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Exporting content in various formats (e.g. pdf, rtf)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Watching for notifications (e.g. rss and/or email)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>Once unstealthed, the tool is added to worksites just like any other tool.
                    Once added, a Wiki space dedicated to that worksite is created with a number of
                    default pages. Members of the worksite may edit the content and create new pages
                    simply by placing Wiki links on the existing pages.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="messagecenter">
            <title>Message Center</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>sakai.messagecenter</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/MFT/Home"
                                >http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/MFT/Home</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Kristol Hancock (khancock@iupui.edu)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para>Message Center is Indiana University’s solution for discussion and private
                    messaging, facilitating one-on-one and group communication. Through private
                    messaging, users within a site can quickly and easily communicate and can even
                    auto-forward private messages to their favorite email client. By providing
                    authors with extensive control over permissions and forum/topic status and
                    giving users a more intuitive navigation, the discussion forum feature
                    complements private messaging well.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>System administrators need to set the role-to-permission-level mapping in
                        <filename>sakai.properties</filename>. OOTB generic roles are set to the
                    following:</para>
                <screen>
mc.default.Student=Contributor
mc.default.Instructor=Owner
mc.default.Teaching\ Assisant=Contributor</screen>
                <para>Note: If you add a role to <filename>sakai.properties</filename> that has a
                    space, you must escape it with a backslash (e.g., <command>mc.default.project\
                        owner=Owner</command>).</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="osp">
            <title>OSP</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>osp.*</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/OSP/Home"
                                >http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/OSP/Home</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Chris Coppola (chris.coppola@rsmart.com)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para>The Open Source Portfolio (OSP) has been a significant standalone product in
                    its own right, and it is bundled in Sakai 2.2 as a suite of tools
                    designed to work in concert for portfolio-based assessment. Using OSP, individuals can collect
                    items, reflect, design portfolios, and publish them to
                    designated audiences. Instructors and program administrators
                    are able to provide structure and guidance to an individual's
                    work that include step-by-step (sequential) wizards, matrices
                    of goals/standards, and hierarchies to organize related work.  Please visit <link
                        xl:href="http://www.osportfolio.org">http://www.osportfolio.org</link> for
                    more information on the Open Source Portfolio (OSP).</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="search">
            <title>Search</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>sakai.search</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link
                                xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/SEARCH/Home"
                                >http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/SEARCH/Home</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Ian Boston (ian@caret.cam.ac.uk)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para>The search tool aims to provide a tool that allows a Google-like search of all
                    content in a Sakai instance. It also provides a service component that can be
                    used by other tools to provide search functionality. When search is turned on,
                    an indexer runs in the background that treats content as it is added to the
                    system, </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>To turn on search indexing, add the following to
                    <filename>sakai.properties</filename>: </para>
                <screen>
search.enable=true</screen>
                <para>To make the tool available, unstealth the tool id
                    <command>sakai.search</command>.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="su">
            <title>SU</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>sakai.su</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>None</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Zach Thomas (zach.thomas@txstate.edu)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para>SU is a tool for administrators to use to log in as another user. It is code
                    developed at Texas State University for their local brand of Sakai called
                        <emphasis>TRACS: Teaching Research and Collaboration System</emphasis>. It
                    is meant to be used within the Admin Workspace, and so it does not need to be
                    stealthed or unstealthed (it will never appear among the tool options in
                    "Worksite Setup"). It features a simple form in which you type the user id of
                    the user you wish to "become" in the system.</para>
                <para>The name stands for Super User, and comes from a command-line tool in Unix
                    that serves the same purpose. It is often pronounced "Sue."</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>

                <para>In order to use the tool, edit the <emphasis>!admin</emphasis> site (i.e. the
                    Admin MyWorkspace) through the admin <emphasis>Sites</emphasis> tool, add a page
                    or edit an existing page, and place the tool on that page. The SU tool will
                    appear in the list with the title "Become User" and the id
                    <emphasis>sakai.su</emphasis>. When you've placed the tool, remember to click
                    the <emphasis>Save</emphasis> button.</para>

                <para>The tool itself is very simple. There is a text field to type a user id, and
                    there is a <emphasis>Submit</emphasis> button. Your session will continue as
                    though you had logged in as the specified user. This will work even if that user
                    is already logged in at another location.</para>

                <para>To change back to "yourself," you must logout and log back in.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Security</title>
                <para>The SU tool is hard-coded only to work for users with administrative
                    privileges. Naturally you should take care whom you give these privileges to.
                    The ability to have more fine-grained control of permissions on the tool may be
                    developed for a future version.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="sakaiscript">
            <title>Sakaiscript</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>NA</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>None</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Steve Githens (s-githens@northwestern.edu)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para>Sakaiscript is essentially a logical web service wrapper to the Sakai API,
                    opening up a number of common admin functions to easy scripting from other
                    languages. You'll find HTML documentation for it, including sample scripts from
                    Python, in
                <filename>reference/docs/webservices/html/index.html</filename>.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>Sakai web services and SakaiScript are included in the release and need to be
                    turned on using a property in the Sakai Properties file:</para>
                <screen>
# Indicates whether or not we allow web-service logins
webservices.allowlogin=false</screen>
                <para>This parameter is set to false so as to make sure that no one can robot-guess
                    Sakai passwords using web services out of the box. If you want to support the
                    login, you must set this property to true in your Sakai instance.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Security</title>
                <para>While it's true that you have to enable the above property to log in via
                    webservices, webservices are always "on". In other words you could, in
                    principle, always navigate to the Axis page to view the SOAP methods, and use
                    SakaiScript as long as you have a SessionID (you could just copy it from your
                    browser cookie).</para>
                <para>Any site enabling web-services should understand the security implications of
                    Sakai web services. Web services should be run over HTTPS in any production
                    environment as IDs, Passwords, and Sakai Session Keys are passed back and forth
                    in plain text using SOAP.</para>
                <para/>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>



        <sect2 xml:id="postem">
            <title>Post 'Em</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>sakai.postem</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/PEM/Home"
                                >http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/PEM/Home</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Kristol Hancock (khancock@iupui.edu)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para><emphasis>Post ‘Em</emphasis> is an automated reporting system that enables
                    faculty to post grades and comments without compromising student privacy.
                        <emphasis>Post ‘Em</emphasis> accepts CSV files, empowering faculty to track
                    student grades in a spreadsheet application of their choice. Keep in mind that
                        <emphasis>Post ‘Em</emphasis> files are not restricted to grades and
                    comments, so the research community may also benefit from this
                functionality.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>The tool simply needs to be unstealthed, and requires no special
                    configuration.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="summarycalendar">
            <title>Summary Calendar</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>sakai.summary.calendar</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link
                                xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/CALSUM/Calendar+Summary"
                                >http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/CALSUM/Calendar+Summary</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Nuno Fernandes (nuno@ufp.pt)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para>Calendar Summary is a synoptic tool that presents a visual monthly view of
                    schedule events in the Home page of My Workspace or other course/project sites.
                    If placed in My Workspace sites, it aggregates schedule events of all active
                    sites the user is member of (unless the user is an admin). If placed in
                    course/project sites, it displays only events for that site.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>This tool may be unstealthed to allow it to be added by site maintainers -
                    just as with most other provisional tools - but it's especially appropriate to
                    add it to site templates. To add it to new My Workspaces by default, for
                    example, edit the <command>!user</command> template. To add it to the Home page
                    of course/project sites, edit the Home page of the <command>!worksite</command>
                    template.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="samigo">
            <title>Tests&amp;Quizzes</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>sakai.samigo</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/SAM/Home"
                                >http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/SAM/Home</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Lydia Li (lydial@stanford.edu)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para>Samigo is the historical project name for the tool that appears in Sakai as
                        <emphasis>Tests&amp;Quizzes</emphasis> (the terms are often used
                    interchangeably). It is an online assessment tool that supports teaching and
                    learning, in both formative assessments and summative assessments.</para>

                <para>Its key features are:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis>Creating Assessments:</emphasis> It supports rich text
                            editing of a variety of question types such as Multiple Choice, Survey,
                            Short Answer/Essay, True/False, Fill in the Blank, File Upload, and
                            Audio Recording. It also allows importing individual questions from
                            question pools, as well as random ones drawn from question pools.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis>Importing/Exporting:</emphasis> Assessments can be
                            exported/imported via IMS QTI xml format. It currently supports QTI
                        1.2.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis>Organizing and Publishing:</emphasis> It allows instructors
                            to specify release date, due date, and/or retract date, late handling,
                            number of submissions, grading options, feedback settings, security
                            settings, and layout...etc. It supports automatic and manual grading; It
                            also provides management for question pools.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis>Managing assessment-taking:</emphasis> It delivers
                            assessments based on a rich set of settings configured during authoring,
                            such as randomized questions and answers, timed assessment with auto
                            submit, high security assessments with restricted IP and secondary
                            password, feedback settings, as well as the option to automatically send
                            grades to Sakai's Gradebook tool.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>Samigo is an ambitious application, and has its own set of release notes
                    maintained on Confluence, which you can find at: <link
                        xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/SAM/2.2+Release+Notes"
                        >http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/SAM/2.2+Release+Notes</link>.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>For File Upload questions in Samigo, answers are saved to DB as a blob by
                    default. If you want to save answers to files, you can override this default by
                    adding the following in your sakai.properties file.</para>

                <screen>
# ** Samigo File Upload question type settings **
# the following default settings
# com.corejsf.UploadFilter.repositoryPath,
# com.corejsf.UploadFilter.sizeThreshold,
# com.corejsf.UploadFilter.sizeMax and
# com.corejsf.UploadFilter.saveMediaToDb in Samigo web.xml
# can be overidden with the following settings in sakai.properties
samigo.answerUploadRepositoryPath=/tmp/
samigo.sizeThreshold=512
samigo.sizeMax=20480
samigo.saveMediaToDb=false</screen>


                <para>When <command>saveMediaToDB</command> is true,
                    <command>SAM_MEDIA_T.MEDIA</command> must be a blob or equivalent to work. If
                    you're running Oracle and using <command>auto.ddl</command> to create tables,
                    you should check the data type of the "MEDIA" column in the
                    <command>SAM_MEDIA_T</command> table. Hibernate tries to choose the right data
                    type for this field, but has a habit of choosing the wrong one for Oracle. The
                    correct types for each database are:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>HSQLDB --> varbinary</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Oracle --> blob</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>MySQL --> longblob</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>For further configuration options and details, please see the Samigo release
                    notes at:<link
                        xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/SAM/2.2+Release+Notes"
                        >http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/SAM/2.2+Release+Notes</link>.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="roster">
            <title>Roster</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>sakai.site.roster</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>None</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Kristol Hancock (khancock@iupui.edu)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para><emphasis>Roster</emphasis> allows users to view the names, photos and
                    profiles of site participants who have made their information accessible through
                    the <emphasis>Profile</emphasis> tool in <emphasis>My Workspace</emphasis>. If
                    an institution has institutional photos, the photos can be made accessible
                    separately to site maintainers.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>The tool simply needs to be unstealthed. It requires no special configuration,
                    but some extra work may need to be done to provide photos for it from campus
                    systems.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="twinpeaks">
            <title>TwinPeaks</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Tool ID:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>None</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Confluence Space:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>None</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Contact:</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Jim Eng (jimeng@umich.edu)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para>TwinPeaks is a capability to search external repositories while using the
                    HTMLArea WYSIWIG editor (note: Sakai 2.2 uses FCKeditor by default). TwinPeaks
                    was originally developed by the Indiana University Library and was extended and
                    merged into the Sakai 2.1 release by the MIT OKI project.</para>

                <para>To add a repository to TwinPeaks, one must write or obtain an OKI DR OSID
                    implementation for that particular repository and then install the OSID
                    implementation in their Sakai instance. Documentation for installing and
                    registering a new OSID implementation within Sakai is available in the Sakai
                    Development Resources area on collab.sakiaproject.org.</para>
                <para>TwinPeaks is suitable for use on development servers and can be used to enable
                    sites to begin the development of their DR OSID implementations. The TwinPeaks
                    implementation in the Sakai 2.2 release should not be turned on in production
                    systems without additional work.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>TwinPeaks can be enabled by changing the following sakai.properties setting to
                    true.</para>

                <screen>
# enable the twinpeaks feature in the WYSIWYG editor in legacy tools: true or false
wysiwyg.twinpeaks=false</screen>

            </sect3>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</article>
