<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0b5/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">

    <info>
        <title>Provisional Tools</title>
        <author>
            <personname>Clay Fenlason</personname>
        </author>
        <edition>15 June 2006 – Document version 2.2</edition>
    </info>

    <sect1 xml:id="provisional">
        <title>What Makes a Tool Provisional</title>
        <para>A provisional tool is one which is considered to be mature enough to be included in
            the release distribution, but is not (yet) considered to be an official part of the
            enterprise bundle, and which does not come enabled by default. Additional steps are
            required to enable these additional tools, per the discretion of the deploying
            institutions or individuals.</para>
        <para>The basic idea of a provisional tools is to allow sites to have readier access to
            these blossoming tools, for testing and evaluation. If they meet needs and success is
            reported in production, they may be included as a standard part of the bundle in future
            releases. Your feedback on the suitability of these tools for inclusion in an upcoming
            Sakai release is therefore an important part of this process.</para>
        <para>You'll find a more complete treatment of the criteria for provisional status among the
            "community practices" posted on Confluence: <link
                xl:href="http://bugs.sakaiproject.org/confluence/display/SCP/Criteria+for+Provisional+Status"
                >Criteria for Provisional Status</link></para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="unstealth">
        <title>Unstealthing Tools</title>
        <para>Provisional tools (among others) are "stealthed" by default. This means they do not
            appear as options in either the <emphasis>Worksite Setup</emphasis> or <emphasis>Edit
                Tools</emphasis> lists - they effectively require the intervention of an admin in
            order to be added to a site.</para>
        <para>Tools can be stealthed through a setting in sakai.properties, which simply contains a
            comma-separated list of all the tool ids for stealthed tools. Sakai OOTB has the
            following tools stealthed:</para>
        <screen>
#stealthTools@org.sakaiproject.tool.api.ActiveToolManager=</screen>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="rwiki">
        <title>Rwiki (sakai.rwiki)</title>
        <para/>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="su">
        <title>SU (sakai.su)</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>What it Is</title>
            <para>SU is a tool for administrators to use to log in as another user. It is code
                developed at Texas State University for their local brand of Sakai called
                    <emphasis>TRACS: Teaching Research and Collaboration System</emphasis>. It is
                meant to be used within the Admin Workspace, and so it does not need to be stealthed
                or unstealthed (it will never appear among the tool options in "Worksite Setup"). It
                features a simple form in which you type the user id of the user you wish to
                "become" in the system.</para>
            <para>The name stands for Super User, and comes from a command-line tool in Unix that
                serves the same purpose. It is often pronounced "Sue."</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Building / Deploying</title>
            <para>The tool is only available to adminstrators and not part of the Adminstrator
                Workspace by default. If you would like to completely remove the SU tool, simply
                delete the entire module at the path /admin-tools/su in the Sakai source
            tree.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Using the Tool</title>
            <para>After the SU tool is deployed, it will appear in the list of tools in the
                Administrative Sites tool. It will NOT appear in the list of tools for the Worksite
                Setup tool, since SU is intended for administrators only, and not for general use.</para>

            <para>In order to use the tool, edit the <emphasis>!admin</emphasis> site (i.e. the
                Admin MyWorkspace) through the admin <emphasis>Sites</emphasis> tool, add a page or
                edit an existing page, and place the tool on that page. The SU tool will appear in
                the list with the title "Become User" and the id <emphasis>sakai.su</emphasis>. When
                you've placed the tool, remember to click the <emphasis>Save</emphasis> button.</para>

            <para>The tool itself is very simple. There is a text field to type a user id, and there
                is a <emphasis>Submit</emphasis> button. Your session will continue as though you
                had logged in as the specified user. This will work even if that user is already
                logged in at another location.</para>

            <para>To change back to "yourself," you must logout and log back in.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Security</title>
            <para>The SU tool is hard-coded only to work for users with administrative privileges.
                Naturally you should take care whom you give these privileges to. The ability to
                have more fine-grained control of permissions on the tool may be developed for a
                future version.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Known Issues</title>
            <para>It's a small thing, but if you click the "View user info" button, the button
                should then become disabled unless the id field should change.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Contact</title>
            <para>Sakai su is written by Zach Thomas at Texas State University. You may contact him
                at zach.thomas@txstate.edu.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sakaiscript">
        <title>Sakaiscript</title>
        <para/>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="roster">
        <title>Roster</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Overview</title>
            <para><emphasis>Roster</emphasis> allows users to view the names, photos and profiles of
                site participants who have made their information accessible through the
                    <emphasis>Profile</emphasis> tool in <emphasis>My Workspace</emphasis>. If an
                institution has institutional photos, the photos can be made accessible separately
                to site maintainers.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Configuration</title>
            <para>The tool simply needs to be unstealthed, and requires no special
            configuration.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="twinpeaks">
        <title>TwinPeaks</title>
        <para/>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="messagecenter">
        <title>Message Center</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Overview</title>
            <para>Message Center is Indiana University’s solution for discussion and private
                messaging, facilitating one-on-one and group communication. Through private
                messaging, users within a site can quickly and easily communicate and can even
                auto-forward private messages to their favorite email client. By providing authors
                with extensive control over permissions and forum/topic status and giving users a
                more intuitive navigation, the discussion forum feature complements private
                messaging well.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Configuration</title>
            <para>System administrators need to set the role-to-permission-level mapping in
                    <filename>sakai.properties</filename>. OOTB generic roles are set to the
                following:</para>
            <screen>
mc.default.Student=Contributor
mc.default.Instructor=Owner</screen>
            <para>Note: If you add a role to <filename>sakai.properties</filename> that has a space,
                you must escape it with a backslash (e.g., <command>mc.default.project\
                owner=Owner</command>).</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="postem">
        <title>Post 'Em</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Overview</title>
            <para><emphasis>Post ‘Em</emphasis> is an automated reporting system that enables
                faculty to post grades and comments without compromising student privacy.
                    <emphasis>Post ‘Em</emphasis> accepts CSV files, empowering faculty to track
                student grades in a spreadsheet application of their choice. Keep in mind that
                    <emphasis>Post ‘Em</emphasis> files are not restricted to grades and comments,
                so the research community may also benefit from this functionality.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Configuration</title>
            <para>The tool simply needs to be unstealthed, and requires no special
            configuration.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="summarycalendar">
        <title>Summary Calendar</title>
        <para/>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="search">
        <title>Search</title>
        <para/>
    </sect1>
</article>
