<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0b5/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">

    <info>
        <title>2.2.0 Release Notes</title>
        <edition>14 July 2006 - version 2.2.0</edition>
    </info>
    <sect1 xml:id="new">
        <title>What's New</title>
        <sect2 xml:id="new-function">
            <title>New Features</title>
            <sect3 xml:id="new-function-group">
                <title>Group Awareness</title>
                <para>Group awareness has been extended to three additional tools: Resources,
                    Assignments, and Schedule.  That is to say, the contents of each of those tools can have their access restricted to specific groups, as they are defined by site maintainers in the <emphasis>Site Info</emphasis> tool.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3 xml:id="new-function-eid">
                <title>EID/UID Separation</title>
                <para>For the last few releases we've been working to introduce the concept of
                    "internal" and "external" identifiers in Sakai in the User records. We started
                    with a single identifier that had to play both of these roles, and have been
                    tweaking the code to separate these out. For 2.2 we have completed this
                    separation.  It is now possible for an institution to, for example, alter the
                    enterprise IDs of their users without losing access to their sites and materials in Sakai. For a
                    thorough discussion of these changes, see the doc
                        <filename>architecture/sakai_id_eid.doc</filename> (or in subversion at:
                        <link
                        xl:href="https://source.sakaiproject.org/svn/reference/branches/sakai_2-2-x/docs/architecture/sakai_id_eid.doc"
                        >https://source.sakaiproject.org/svn/reference/trunk/docs/architecture/sakai_id_eid.doc</link>)</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>FCKeditor</title>
                <para>The FCKeditor WYSIWYG editor was available in 2.1, but not the default. In 2.2
                    it has become the default editor.  HTMLArea is still included, however, and the default editor may be overridden in <filename>sakai.properties</filename> by altering the following setting:</para>
                <screen>
# specify the wysiwyg editor 
wysiwyg.editor=FCKeditor</screen>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Included Skins</title>
                <para>The three highest-scoring skins from the recent skins contest have been
                    included in the distribution.  You can make any of these your default skin by using the following property in <filename>sakai.properties</filename> (other possible values are commented out):</para>
                <screen>
# The default skin for sites without a skin setting
# skin.default=gen-u
# skin.default=examp-u
# skin.default=some-u
skin.default=default</screen>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Updated Help Content</title>
                <para>Help Content in 2.1 was out of date, reflecting only version 2.0 of the
                    software. The help content has been updated for 2.2, along with some style
                    improvements.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>French and Japanese translations</title>
                <para>New interface translations for French and Japanese have been included. See
                        <filename>reference/docs/readme_i18n.txt</filename> for more information on
                    the translations.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="new-provisional">
            <title>New Provisional Tools</title>
            <para>Sakai 2.2.0 has added four new provisional tools</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Message Center </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a tool combining a discussion forum with private messaging.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Search </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a tool providing a Google-like search of all site content.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Summary Calendar </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a synoptic calendar view for the <emphasis>MyWorkspace</emphasis> that includes events from
                            all the sites to which a user is a member.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Post 'Em </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>an automated reporting system that enables faculty to post grades and
                            comments without compromising student privacy. Post ‘Em accepts CSV
                            files, empowering faculty to track student grades in a spreadsheet
                            application of their choice.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>You can find more details about these and all other provisional tools on the <link xl:href="http://source.sakaiproject.org/2.2.0/provisional.html">provisional tools</link> page.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="migration">
        <title>Migration Issues</title>
        <sect2 xml:id="migration-conversion">
            <title>DB Conversion</title>
            <para>There are database schema changes between 2.1.2 and 2.2.0, and the conversion
                scripts to be applied - in distinct versions for MySQL and Oracle, respectively -
                are found in the <filename>reference/docs/updating</filename> folder of the release
                or on subversion:</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>MySQL</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link
                                xl:href="https://source.sakaiproject.org/svn/reference/branches/sakai_2-2-x/docs/conversion/sakai_2_1_2-2_2_0_mysql_conversion.sql"
                                >https://source.sakaiproject.org/svn/reference/branches/sakai_2-2-x/docs/conversion/sakai_2_1_2-2_2_0_mysql_conversion.sql</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Oracle</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link
                                xl:href="https://source.sakaiproject.org/svn/reference/branches/sakai_2-2-x/docs/conversion/sakai_2_1_2-2_2_0_oracle_conversion.sql"
                                >https://source.sakaiproject.org/svn/reference/branches/sakai_2-2-x/docs/conversion/sakai_2_1_2-2_2_0_oracle_conversion.sql</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>In the same directory you'll also find conversion scripts for earlier Sakai
                versions. Migration from an earlier version will require the successive application
                of all intermediate update scripts. You cannot, for example, move from 2.1.1 to
                2.2.0 by applying a single DB script. You will need to move first from 2.1.1 to
                2.1.2, and then to 2.2.0.</para>
            <note>
                <title>Examine before using</title>
                <para>As a general rule, be sure to read through these conversion scripts before
                    applying them. They do not take into account any special customizations you may
                    have made - such as new roles, or the deployment of additional tools - and they
                    may complicate your migration with unintended consequences if you execute the
                    script blindly.</para>
                <para>For the 2.2.0 release, the <emphasis>Message Center</emphasis> tool is one
                    such particular example. A number of schools deployed <emphasis>Message
                    Center</emphasis> in 2.1.x production instances, before it was yet a provisional
                    tool. Now that <emphasis>Message Center</emphasis> is a provisional tool in
                    2.2.0, the conversion scripts were written to alter the database to introduce
                    them, and thus assume that <emphasis>Message Center</emphasis> is a new tool for
                    your instance. If it isn't, you'll want to comment out the portions of the
                    conversion script that treat it, and instead execute the following conversions:</para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>MySQL</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <screen>
ALTER TABLE MFR_TOPIC_T ADD DEFAULTASSIGNNAME VARCHAR(255);
ALTER TABLE MFR_OPEN_FORUM_T ADD DEFAULTASSIGNNAME VARCHAR(255);
ALTER TABLE MFR_MESSAGE_T ADD GRADEASSIGNMENTNAME VARCHAR(255);
ALTER TABLE MFR_MESSAGE_T ADD GRADECOMMENT VARCHAR(255);</screen>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Oracle</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <screen>
ALTER TABLE MFR_TOPIC_T ADD DEFAULTASSIGNNAME VARCHAR2(255) NULL;
ALTER TABLE MFR_OPEN_FORUM_T ADD DEFAULTASSIGNNAME VARCHAR2(255) NULL;
ALTER TABLE MFR_MESSAGE_T ADD GRADEASSIGNMENTNAME VARCHAR2(255) NULL;
ALTER TABLE MFR_MESSAGE_T ADD GRADECOMMENT VARCHAR2(255) NULL;</screen>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </note>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="migration-api">
            <title>API Changes and sakai.properties</title>
            <para>The 2.2 refactoring means that many package names have changed, and these
                differences will mainly be encountered in <filename>sakai.properties</filename>
                settings which reference beans. It's best to not try to use a
                    <filename>sakai.properties</filename> from a previous release, and instead start
                with the sample in <filename>reference/docs/sakai.properties</filename>.</para>
            <para>Any custom code, such as providers, may also need revision. See below for more
                discussion of providers in particular.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="migration-providers">
            <title>Provider Changes</title>
            <para>As mentioned above, 2.2 introduces a separation of external user identifiers from
                Sakai's internal user ids. Any custom <filename>UserDirectoryProvider</filename>
                will need some alteration to account for this, along with changes to its import
                statements and declarations that stem from API changes. Below is a list of changes
                that a typical provider should require:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Import statements altered to reflect new package names.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A search and replace to turn getters and setters from, e.g., 'getId' to
                        'getEid'.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Revise the project.xml files in both the provider module and 'component'
                        with the appropriate UDP location.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Change the Spring bean declaration in component.xml.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The UDP class may implement the DisplayAdvisor (optional), and the two
                        additional methods this pulls in. </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Skin Changes</title>
            <para>A number of CSS changes will need to be made to any 2.1 skins in order to adapt them to 2.2.  These changes - including conversion steps - are thoroughly documented in the appendices of the skin document available in reference/docs/architecture, or in subversion at:  <link xl:href="https://source.sakaiproject.org/svn/reference/branches/sakai_2-2-x/docs/architecture/sakai_skin.doc">https://source.sakaiproject.org/svn/reference/branches/sakai_2-2-x/docs/architecture/sakai_skin.doc</link></para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="maintenance">
        <title>Maintenance Branch</title>
        <para>The code of each release has a corresponding maintenance branch, which is patched with fixes in an ongoing way by a branch manager - effectively until there is no longer sufficient interest in it for a branch manager to volunteer.  Maintenance branches therefore represent the latest stable snapshot of any given Sakai version.</para>
        <para>These maintenance branches may be checked out through subversion, they are labeled with an 'x' replacing their minor version number, e.g. '2-2-x'.  You can check out the 2.2 maintenance branch with the following command: </para>
        <para><command>svn co https://source.sakaiproject.org/svn/sakai/branches/sakai_2-2-x/</command></para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="resolved">
        <title>Fixes Included in this Release</title>
        <para/>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="open-issues">
        <title>Open Issues</title>
        <para/>
    </sect1>
</article>
